Guide to the Clarence E. Larson Science and Technology Oral History collection, 1983-1993
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Clarence E. Larson Science and Technology Oral History collection
1983-1993
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Clarence E. Larson
C0079
3 linear feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains 49 videotape cassettes, some of which have been copied to DVD, featuring interviews with famous scientists and historians of twentieth-century technology conducted by Clarence E. Larson.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Clarence Larson in 1993.
Biographical Information
Chemist Clarence E. Larson (1909-1999) was born in Cloquet, Minnesota. He graduated from the University of Minnesota with a degree in Chemistry and completed his Ph.D. work at the University of California at Berkeley. Larson was one of the talented American scientists working on the Manhattan Project during World War II. Later he served as a director at Oak Ridge National Laboratory, a member of the Atomic Energy Commission, and an executive at Union Carbide. Dr Larson was a recipient of the Distinguished Achievement Award of the American Society for the Advancement of Science. He was also a member of the American Nuclear Society, the American Institute of Chemists, the American Chemical Society, and the Cosmos Club.
Scope and Content
This collection contains 49 videotape cassettes, some of which have been copied to DVD, featuring interviews with famous scientists and historians of twentieth-century technology conducted by Clarence E. Larson.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by surname of interviewee.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other science and technology collections, such as the Harold Morowitz papers and the.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Science--History--20th century.; Technology.
Contents List
- Larson Clarence Collection
  - Abelson, Phil (1913-2004) 12-20-83 (Box 1)
    Co-discoverer of the first transuranic element. Inventor of thermal diffusion for uranium isotope production. Bethesda, MD. 17 minutes.
  - Agnew, Harold, UCSD (1921- ) 12-21-83 (Box 1)
    Crew of the first sustaining reactor. Fermi Award winner. La Jolla, CA. 11 minutes.
  - Alvarez, Luis (1911-1988) 3-13-84 (Box 1)
    Inventor of ground control radar. Developer of high energy linear accelerators. Nobel Prize winner.
  - Arnold, William (Box 1)
    Originator of the word fission, while he worked with Niels Bohr in Copenhagen in 1938.
  - Atanasoff, John V. (1903-1995) (Box 1)
  - Bacher, Robert (1905-2004) (Box 1)
    Pioneer in nuclear energy research.
  - Backus, John (1924- ) (Box 1)
  - Bechtel, Steve Sr. (1900-1989) 7-10-84 (Box 1)
    San Francisco, CA. 30 minutes.
  - Blueprint for Space- Science Fiction to Science Fact- Hosted by Astronaut Alan Shepard (Box 1)
  - Brobeck, William (1908-1998) (Box 1)
  - Calvin, Melvin (1911-1997) (Box 1)
    Berkeley, CA. 25 minutes.
  - Clarke, C. Arthur- "A Failed Recluse" (1917- ) copy (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Karl (Box 1)
  - Delbecco, Rene 3-25-86 (Box 2)
    La Jolla, CA. 25 minutes.
  - Djerassi, Dr. Carl (1923- ) 7-12-84 (Box 2)
    Copies 1, 2
  - Edgerton, H.E. (1889-1990) (Box 2)
  - Eklund, Dr. Sigurd 4-30-84 (Box 2)
    Bethesda, MD. 18 minutes.
  - Glennan, Dr. Keith (1905-1995) (Box 2)
  - Goldschmidt, Dr. Bertrand (1913-2002) 12-7-83 (Box 2)
    Nuclear pioneer starting with work with Madam Curie. Bethesda, MD. 18 minutes.
  - Hafstad, Dr. Lawrence (1904-1993) (Box 2)
    Discoverer of delayed Neutrons. 41 minutes.
  - Hoff, Dr. Ted (1937- ) 12-22-88 (Box 2)
  - Hollaender, Dr. Alexander (1898-1997) 12-20-83 (Box 2)
    Bethesda, MD. 16 minutes.
  - Hurd, Cuthbert (1911-1996) (Box 2)
    Pioneer in computer science. Started IBM computer project.
  - Jukes, Thomas (1906-1999) (Box 2)
  - Kamen, Dr. Martin (1913-2002) 3-24-86 (Box 2)
    Santa Barbara, CA. 14 minutes.
  - Magoun, Dr. Horace (1907-1991) 8-20-84 (Box 3)
    Los Angeles, CA.
  - McMillan, Dr. Edwin (1907-1991) 3-15-84 (Box 3)
    Co-discoverer of Neptunium and Plutonium. Nobel prize winner. Inventor of synchrotron.
  - Nichols, Kenneth David (1907-2000) 11-6-85 (Box 3)
    General manager of the Manhattan Project. General manager of the Atomic Energy Commission. Bethesda, MD. 20 minutes.
  - Oliphant, Dr. Mark (1901-2000) 11-3-88 (Box 3)
    Bethesda, MD.20 minutes.
  - Packard, David (1912-1996) 3-15-84 (Box 3)
    Co-Founder of Hewlitt-Packard Corporation. Deputy Secretary of Defense.Copy 1.
  - Pauling, Linus (1901-1994) 2-12-93 (Box 3)
    Chemical bond theory. Winner of two Nobel Prizes. Copy 1 (Cassette 1 of 2)
  - Pauling, Linus (Box 3)
    Chemical bond theory. Winner of two Nobel Prizes. Cassette 2 of 2.
  - Peierls, Rudolph (1907-1995) 4-25-89 (Box 3)
    Bethesda, MD. 27 minutes.
  - Pioneers- Djerassi, Hollifield, Goldschmidt, Bechtel, Packardi, and Pauling (Box 3)
  - Rush, Dr. Kenneth 11-6-85 (Box 3)
    Bethesda, MD. 19 minutes.
  - Schawlow, Dr. Arthur (1921-1999) 10-28-84 (Box 3)
    Palo Alto, CA. 28 minutes.
  - Seaborg, Dr. Glenn (1927-1999) 12-29-93 (Box 3)
    Co-discoverer of Plutonium. Nobel Prize winer. Discovery of many transuranic elements. Copy 1.
  - Segre, Emilio (1905-1989) 3-20-84 (Box 3)
    Discovery of slow Neutrons and anti-proton. Nobel Prize winer. Copy 1.
  - Singer, S. Fred (1924- ) (Box 4)
    Pioneer in space research.
  - Starr, Dr. Chauncey (1912- ) 12-20-85 (Box 4)
  - Stehling, Dr. Kurtiz (Box 4)
  - Tape, Dr. Gerald (1915-1905) 4-30-84 (Box 4)
    Fundamental research on radar and nuclear science. Bethesda, MD. 23 minutes.
  - Taylor, Lauriston (1902-2004) (Box 4)
    Pioneer in radiation reseaech.
  - Teller, Dr.Edward (1908-2003) 12-29-83 (Box 4)
    Pioneer in nuclear theory. Fermi Award Winner. Copy 1.
  - Townes, Dr. Charles (1915- ) 3-21-84 (Box 4)
    Inventor of Maser-Laser Principle.Nobel Prize winner. Copy 1.
  - Weinberg, Alvin (1915-2006) 3-21-84 (Box 4)
    Washington, D.C. 12 minutes.
  - White, Dr. Robert 4-25-89 (Box 4)
    Development of modern weather forecasting. President of National Academy of Engineering. Bethesda, MD. 27 minutes.
  - Wigner, E.P. (1902-1995) 3-4-86 (Box 4)
    Instrumental with Szilard in persuading President Roosevelt to start Nuclear Energy Project. Nobel Prize winner in Physics.
  - DVD Copies (Box 5)
    DVD copies of many of the interviews.